And then um once it starts uh and it has
started now I am admitting everybody
from the lobby. Oh, we do have a couple.
We've got Larry there. I'll promote him.
Um and then it just takes a moment or
two as usual for everyone to come in
from the lobby. And so um please be
patient with us everybody as we get
everybody in from that lobby. Um, and
good morning. While that's happening,
uh, this is Dr. Dominic Erllo. I am the
director for the Center for Medical
Cannabis and Psilocybin. And this is
the, uh, medical psilocybin advisory
board training and education committee
meeting with Brenda Burgard as the
chair. The department is here of course
to support the meeting. And to do that,
as a reminder, this meeting is being
recorded and so please keep language uh
appropriate for all ages as we do post
these up on our website. And so with
that, I will turn it on over to you,
Brenda.
>> Ah, thank you, Dominic. Thank you
everybody for coming this morning. Um, I
want to thank um, Robert and Jonathan
and uh, Leslie and Larry and everyone
else that's coming to this uh, meeting
today. Uh, I know we've been really
working over uh, the practicum and the
didactic hours really hard here. So, I
think that we're really really close to
finding a consensus on what needs to be
uh added to the hours uh for both of
those um items. So, uh if you could um I
don't know if you have control over
Dominic or um Jorge or is is Jorge here
today or is it John?
>> So, uh uh Jorge is not here today. He is
actually on leave today, but um I have
the um uh I'll be posting up the various
items as we normally do. Which document
would you like, Brenda? [snorts]
>> Um I think we'll start with um uh well,
we can't split the screen. So, let's
start with what um
the department of training and education
have first. uh especially with Annne
Mets's um uh and Larry Leman have worked
on. And let's take a look at that first.
>> Give me just a moment to get that one.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. It we have to do octopus arms to
kind of get that up there.
>> Yeah. So, give me just a moment. While
that's happening, do you do people want
to just introduce themselves
>> and just raise your hand if you need to?
Okay. Um, Sky Rivers is saying good
morning here. Let me get into the chat
here.
Um, let's see. Kate Hawk is here and
she's a psychedelic educator from Santa
Fe. I wanted to say Sky Rivers is from
the Santa Fe Reporter.
Um, anyone else? Uh, Gregory Evans um is
here. Uh, did you want to say anything?
Uh, Gregory?
>> Yeah, good morning. Um, my name is
Gregory Evans. I'm an independent
researcher
based in Santa Fe. Um, [clears throat]
as we get started,
um, I would personally love to hear like
what our scope for today's
meeting is and what what our goals are
and what we need to achieve. If we could
start there.
>> Okay. uh
>> kind of a lot is riding on today's
meeting I feel and there some clarity
needs to be
>> achieved.
>> Yes, and I agree with you 100% there. Um
maybe we will be able to look at both of
these things because um as Dominic has
uh mentioned um uh previously that we're
really close to coming to a consensus
about this and my hope is is that uh
either we'll get really close or maybe
we'll have a consensus about this today.
um we don't know but uh let's go ahead
and continue with any other
introductions that we have at this
moment and any other comments
>> and Brenda just to let you know once we
finish with that I do have that document
open and ready.
>> Okay, let's give everybody a minute.
Yeah.
>> Yeah. I didn't want to share it on
screen and detract from introductions.
Okay.
Okay, with that, um, I think we can
start now.
Okay, sorry, there's a lot of things
blocking my screen right now. Okay,
there we go.
>> Okay, and it should be open and people
should be able to see it. I'm going to
just increase the font a little bit.
>> Yes, so people can read. So, there we
go.
So in this um part of uh the summary of
the recommendation and rules the
education training requirements for New
Mexico medical psilocybin program uh
this is what we've got so far from
education and training and so I'll just
briefly go over what uh this is a
document um and to show in plain
language in this this um diagram here
that
um it covers uh three roles of
certifying clinicians uh who are
diagnosed qualifying clinicians and
clear patients for psilocybin therapy,
licensed providers, professionals
holding a license to deliver medical
counseling, mental health or behavioral
health care and facilitators who support
patients through psilocybin sessions in
a nonclinical role. The requirements are
calibrated to rigorous enough to protect
the public while remaining lean enough
that training stays financially
accessible. For a licensed clinician,
every required hour is both in and out
of pocket costs and foregone uh client
hours. Hours uh figures throughout are
minimums. Actual total varies somewhat
by student since not every
administration session lasts a full
eight hours and hours earned
simultaneously count only once towards
the aggregated. So let's pull this up
just a moment here and let's take a
really good look at what we have so far.
So, [clears throat] I wanted to mention
that Kate I'm not Kate, I'm sorry,
[gasps] that Ann Mets and Larry Leman
have been working both on um uh getting
the hours to where it would be
appropriate for um you know for didactic
hours and practicum and so far this is
what we have. Um the required hours for
this first segment for the didactic
um is 8 that's required by certified
clinicians. Uh licensed provider is
required is 80 and a phil uh the
facilitator is 80. So, um, you know, the
certified clinicians, we're, um, I just
wanted to clarify here, the certified
clinicians would be, um, someone with,
um, that's reciprocity. Is that what
we're talking about right here, Dominic?
>> I I mean, any any of the different
levels could potentially get uh,
reciprocity.
So, uh, I mean, it just depends on uh,
if they've been trained in other
locations.
Okay, because I'm going to be asking a
lot of like elementary questions here
because I think that um you know, we
just wanted to simplify the
clarification here and um I like to uh
be explained to as um a a four-year-old.
So, [laughter]
that's how uh to try to boil it down to
basic things. Um I see that uh Gregory,
you have a comment.
>> Yeah. Um, Eli 5, explain it like I'm
five is my primary ethos. So if you if
you love that, go go go find that on
Reddit and and it So one of the things
that I wanted to point out here, I love
to see that we have the adjusted
language for the providers as licensed
providers.
Um I think that is adds a lot of clarity
with the certifying clinician that is
like the medical screener right so the
idea of that person needing a lot of
reciprocity doesn't seem massive like
most of that 8 hours to me sounds like
it would be the New Mexico mo module
what you need to know for New Mexico and
that sort of stuff along with some of
the basic medical information that you
need to do screening. Um I think that
there is potentially a pathway for like
some level of reciprocity, but uh help
me understand
what the real like who like where are
the real like where else do we have this
where people have had the type of
education that qualifies them under a
state program or like a regulated
program to do that work. Is there an
actual reciprocity path?
Um, with the licensed providers and the
facilitators, there's much more of that.
Whereas the certifying clinician is like
a medical screening process. I don't
know. I mean, forgive my ignorance, but
I don't know if that really has
uh Yeah. I don't like is that is that
question clear? I got
>> Yeah, I I I Yeah, I get what you're
saying. is like okay so if you um are
coming in with reciprocity as I know it
um that uh you already have been um uh
pretty you know gone through with the DO
about all of the the uh competencies
that you have from that particular
um uh
learning process that you did like maybe
in another state like Colorado uh and
went through like the Phil or something
like that where [clears throat] those
competencies uh we are acknowledging as
reciprocity
and you know all you need is the New
Mexico module to fulfill that. Is that
what you're asking?
Well, I think Dominic might have some uh
clarity to offer, but like we need to
define what the certifi certifying
clinician is actually doing and what
that is that a medical screening or is
that like um I'll just let Dominic
address this.
>> Yeah. Okay.
>> Thank you. So, with regard to this, so
first of all, neither of these documents
that we're really talking about today
are about the reciprocity piece. Um, but
just to clarify, so any of the different
levels of providers, if they have been
trained elsewhere, so if they've gone
through a certified program or a
licensed program in Colorado or or or
Oregon and they meet the other
requirements of that particular level of
provider. So in the case of a certifying
clinician, can they do the diagnosis and
have the CS number according to the
proposed rules we have currently?
um then and they've gone through a
training in either Oregon or Colorado,
they're able to show it, then they would
be granted the certification and this is
up until December 31st of 2027 in all
cases, but uh they would be granted the
certification to be able to practice
with regard to the program here in New
Mexico. Um and so that's at all of the
levels. The biggest difference is the
certified clinician does not need to
have the um a practicum piece if they
have done the training in other states.
However, the the other providers so the
practic uh the practitioners or licensed
providers and the facilitators will have
had to demonstrate 40 hours contact
hours of doing practicum with patients.
And so that's the biggest difference as
far as the reciprocity for a program to
get reciprocity. In other words, for a
training program to be granted that
ability if they are in another
jurisdiction, so Colorado, Oregon, or
even Australia, Canada, anywhere, they
just have to have uh and have been pro
um licensed or permitted uh approved by
that jurisdiction. So like state of
Colorado, Oregon, etc. Um that's the
biggest part. There is also a piece that
we added on in um because we recognize
there are also some of the uh programs
which are not necessarily recognized in
Colorado or Oregon but have been some of
the forefront and the leaders to ensure
that they actually had been also created
with either uh institutes of higher
education or with regard to research
programs. So for example, if there had
been a program developed um here at UNM
with you know Dr. Leman's program that
was doing education then that could
potentially for example be included in
this um then we also are allowing that
that allows for some of the programs who
are some of the quite frankly the the
gold standards and the originators and
people who got trained at them for
example MAPS is a great example um that
they then would also be eligible for
reciprocity and so we wanted to ensure
that was there um so hopefully that
helps to answer that. So we have a large
part about reciprocity because we heard
very clearly from everybody that how do
we do this for people who have been
trained previously sometimes even
trained prior to other programs coming
online um and how do we actually help to
do that because we recognize that
expertise and that dedication of many of
those individuals.
>> Thank you Dominic. Um, uh, any I would
like to do like a popcorn style today
because, um, I think like going through
all of these, uh, in in detail is going
to be more, uh, information that we can,
you know, think about more. Okay,
Gregory. [clears throat]
>> Yeah, thank you, Dominic. That's um I
like the idea that like uh CES
[clears throat] provided by at
psychedelic science on contraindications
could qualify as didactic or qualify as
potentially reciprocation
that could be considered reciprocity. Um
but yeah, I I do think that we should
push for um shifting the language on the
certifying clinician or defining what
the certific
certifying clinician is going to be
doing. If it is a medical screening and
that's all they're doing and defining
medical readiness and
um [clears throat]
uh analyzing contra indications and not
dealing with any of the certification of
the condition which is in my
understanding the responsibility of the
licensed provider. I think the that
that um it makes it clear that that role
doesn't need a ton of stuff which it
clearly doesn't have and it's not that
complicated.
>> Thank you, Greg.
>> But yeah, moving on.
>> Yeah, and Greg, you you basically have
hit it and essentially the certifying
clinician, all they are doing is
ensuring the medical clearance so that
the person does indeed have the
diagnosis. you know for that particular
condition and that from a medical
standpoint that going through a
psilocybin treatment would be
appropriate. The provider side actually
handles the part of whether or not from
a counseling therapy standpoint it would
be appropriate.
>> Thank you Dominic. Um so um as you can
see in the next segment here
um practicum and supervi supervision you
know we oh here let's go back to the
first one
um practice now um here we could see
that um license provider
uh it's actually supposed to be what 75
is it It says 7S, but we haven't had
time to correct that. I think it says
it's 72 or 7. I think it's 70.
I think it's 72. I think that's what
it's supposed to be. Plus 42
equals 114 hours for the licensed
provider. So, um this is what we're
we're looking at as far as this is our
um our our range here as far as um
practicum and supervision
uh goes and then uh with the co with the
facilitator it's 62 plus the 42 hours is
102 hours. So you could see that the
hours here have been uh uh there's
there's a difference between these two
um that uh were uh the hours have been
increased here and then down below
emergency response credentials um are
required like um you know CPR from the
licensed provider and the facilitator
and that's for when uh if any you know
any emergencies come up while there is a
session. Um and then uh continuing
education every two years which is eight
hours by the um certified certifying
clinician and uh 20 hours by the
licensed provider and 20 hours by the
facilitator. And these are are pretty
much uh the 20 hours of the licensed
provider and facilitator. Uh this is
pretty much uh CEUs that you need to do
every two years in order to maintain uh
good standing for the counseling board
and licensing board. Okay.
Thank you, Larry. It's 72 hours. Thank
you. All right. Uh so we could pull up.
Okay. So here we are with the paracticum
hours which is um this is what we're
this is our range. So, um the 102 is
really what uh the training in and
education
uh what we've come up with and the 114
hours is what the um uh do has come up
with. So, what we're looking at here,
maybe we can increase this a little bit.
I've got my glasses on trying to see
this
>> Brenda. Actually, the 102 and 114 is
actually what the training and education
subgroup Oh, that's what we did. Okay.
>> Yeah, this is the 102 is for
facilitators and the 10 114 is the
licensed providers on on this aspect.
>> Okay. Thanks for the cor clarifying that
because I kind of got a little uh in my
head here. So, uh the New Mexico module
in the dactic hours is 80 um over here
to the uh left side. And then as we get
into the into this uh we're going uh the
well participants is 24 hours. The
second to the co-f facilitation is 24
and then the group work is 12. So
basically doing uh group work of of 12
hours uh is what we've been coming up
with. And then uh on number four
provider supervisory uh 12 hours on the
licensed practitioner track only. And
then uh in uh number five we have 42
hours which is 24 hours supervision
practice and which is two cases and 18
hours consultation group including
presentation of two cases. And then um
after um 48 hours of stage 1 and stage
two high acuity care alongside a
licensed provider hours may be earned
simultaneously.
Each actual hour counts once towards the
total. So you're basically what we're
saying here, right, Dominic, that you
could be doing one part of this and like
individual sessions and you could be
doing group work in order to to get a
total of all of these hours that are
required and and then uh the DO
certification. Um uh after that uh does
anyone have any questions about this
or comments?
Okay, I think we can scroll up and I can
go ahead and read these mod what the
modules have here. Uh, the New Mexico
module required of everyone. Every
certifying clinician, licensed provider,
and facilitator must complete a New
Mexico educational module created or
approved by the department before
applying for certification.
This applies equally to applicants
trained in other juris jurisdictions and
there is no exception for reciprocity.
The module covers the New Mexico medical
psilocybin act and overview of
psilocybin in New Mexico medical
therapeutic model
the social cultural and historical
aspects of psilocybin use including
traditional use by Native American and
other populations in New Mexico.
spiritual
uh existential, religious and
theological theert aspects of psilocybin
therapy and the state programs research
and data collection requirements. It
includes with an elevate elevation
demonstrating competencies in each area.
And let's see the second part here is
certifying clinicians trainings in eight
didactic hours.
Certifying clinicians complete a module
of eight at least eight didactic hours
before applying for certification.
The module addresses psilocybin action
interactions and pharmarmacology. The
responsibilities of the certifying
clinician role. Federal confidentiality
requirements under the 42 CFR part two.
Diagnosis of qualifying conditions.
determining medical clearance for
psilocybin therapy, psychedelic
emergencies, urgencies and medical
monitoring and supporting patients with
challenging experience including
hallucinogen persisting perceptions
disorder HPPPD.
Like the New Mexico module, it is it
ends with a competency evaluation. So,
we're we're we're making sure that each
one of these certifying training pro uh
parts of these programs, we're
evaluating each part of them. So, we're
making sure that uh we're doing our due
diligence with um at least getting these
didactic hours for the certifying
clinician licensed provider and
facilitator training 80 didactic hours.
Licensed providers and facilitators
complete a psilocybin therapy module of
at least 80 didactic hours before
applying for certification. That places
New Mexico below Oregon's 120 hours and
Colorado's 150. A deliberate calibration
since graduates in both states report
that longer didactic requirements did
not buy greater depth. So, in other
words, yeah, um we don't want to do
overkill here with the dactic hours and
that um you know, we don't want to have
a lot of fluff with with the education.
You know, we want to really educate
everyone uh where it needs to be and not
try to
um add more hours to a program that
really doesn't need it. Okay, let's
scroll.
Okay, here you can see in the New Mexico
proposal uh we have in dark green the 80
hours, Oregon is the 120 hours and
Colorado is 150. So this gives a nice
graphic on uh what we're really looking
at here in New Mexico about as far as
the hours are. So within the 80 hours
the rule sets the minimum for the nine
content areas. Here in the content area,
the core psychotherapy skills and ethics
including patient center approaches and
care, cultural competencies, patient
confidentiality,
informed con consent,
self-care and somatic awareness. Um, and
so I'll just wait for Dominic to cut and
paste there.
Okay, thank you. Um so uh we're looking
at the sematic awareness and touch and
that's 42 CFR part two and that's 22
hours. Um end of life and palative care
considerations that's eight uh trauma
and trauma-informed care is seven
preparation and integration sessions.
Six, medicine, dosing, clinical
research, including psilocybin actions,
interactions, and pharmarmacology.
That's five. Screening, suicidality, and
crisis response is five. Administration
sessions, including set and setting
non-ordinary states of consciousness and
use of music is four. Management of tr
challenging psychedelic experiences
including deescalation techniques is
four. Role-playing and or simulation
patient experiences two. And total
specific minimums is 63. So right now
I'll just kind of hold it right there.
Does anybody have any questions for me
or Dominic about anything here? Okay,
Greg.
Is anyone surprised that I have
questions?
>> All righty. Go ahead.
>> Um, [clears throat]
oh, just to clarify, this is really
granular and I think wonderful. Are we
putting this forward as
in rules interpretation or are we
putting this section together as like
best practice recommendations?
because I think we're bridging on the
idea that like we're starting to tell
schools how to break down their
curriculum and I just want to be careful
about how much um
in the words of a wise wizard
Dominic has always said something about
like kind of like dial it back a little
bit to allow for like some breathing
room and flexibility and departmental
discretion um to just kind like sanity
checking that.
>> Okay, good question. Um, so Dominic, you
could answer this one. This is I, you
know, as I'm looking at it, um is more
of the guidelines for um uh education
and and and what we're trying to do as
far as meeting the competencies in uh in
all of these modules that are that uh
these areas in these modules need to
cover. So, uh, as far as education goes,
uh, we're looking at, you know, hey, you
know, let's say, um, you needed, uh, you
know, you were going through the the pro
the education program and, uh, the I'll
take for example, the preparation and
integration sessions are six. So if I'm
a teacher, I need to have that at least
6 hours in that in my module to cover
the preparation and integration
sessions. Um Dominic, then I wanted to
ask you about the other part of it. Are
is this going to be in like the the the
rules? I know this is part of the
competency, but um would that be in what
we're trying to state as far as rules
go?
>> Okay. Thank you, Brenda. And thank you
Greg for the question. So just to be
clear, this particular document we've
been going through is not from the
department of health. This is from the
training and education subcommittee that
was meeting separately. And other than
that final meeting earlier this week
with Brenda and uh Denali and Dr. Leman,
um the department was not in those
meetings in particular. So how that
group was actually intending this to be
written into the rules, I can't answer
that. What I will say, and Greg sort of
mentioned this, and is that when we're
really looking at rules, we we don't
want to turn around for curricula to say
in the different competency areas, here
are specific hours that need to be met.
That it's really more about allowing
those education programs and even with
specific classes to be able to adjust
it. So it really the what the final
recommendation from this group is is it
it's up to this group to make that
determination. Um what I will say is
when I do show what we've been doing as
far as the um from the do side and what
we have is it does not put the minimum
hours. It does have the content as far
as the topics that need to be covered
but does leave how that gets spread
apart between the different classes and
in the curriculum that is up to the
educational programs and those
individual teachers. And part of the
reason why we do that is because for
example if you had an entire class of
individuals who say for example were
already um end of end of life doulas and
so they already have a lot of
information about end of life and
palative care 8 hours may not be enough
with in order to cover that particular
topic or I'm sorry eight hours may be
too much because they already have it
and so then spending some of that time
in other areas would be appropriate.
If in a different class you had no
individuals or only one or two of
individuals who had experience with
regard to end of life and palative care,
you might need to spend a lot more area
or a lot more time in that particular
topic area, but they might then be, you
know, very used to dealing with things
such as trauma or trauma informed care.
And so you want to be able to provide
that sort of flexibility. And so within
the rules themselves, we do we tend not
to put break it down into specific
hours. Um but that really the you know
the recommendation because remember out
of this committee is the recommendation.
That recommendation is up to this
committee to decide. But I would really
recommend from a content area. The
content areas are there. How many
minimum hours overall be there? But as
far as actually allocating to each
content area, that actually creates
restrictions for individuals in training
programs.
>> Thank you, Dominic. Um, who Okay, who
Okay, Greg, did you
>> just a brief
>> Yeah, just a brief response to that.
Thank you, Dominic. Um, I think as a
committee member, I would
[clears throat] recommend that we all
kind of just wrap our heads around what
was just said and understand that all
the like this information right here is
really good. I think that having this on
record available for
um best practices and th those documents
will exist and move forward. just
preparing ourselves for what the
department has just said like they will
zoom out a bit when in the language of
the rules and I don't think that like
should diminish the value of this
breakdown. Um but what we've experienced
in the past was like oh this isn't what
we were expecting to see but just
understanding the that those rules might
be written a little bit differently and
I think that there is good reason for
that. Um but I think we should maintain
um continuing to break down these best
practices and pushing those forward as
such as opposed to specific granular
rules that comment complete.
>> Thank you. Um Larry,
>> yeah um I I think there's a balance here
a little bit. Um I think that you know
for instance we put in end of life care
considerations at eight hours. Um I I
think it'd be fine if a program didn't
have eight hours, but then I think they
should be able to be making an argument
that that they are covering it in enough
that people are having um some level of
competency in that. Um I I think there
are some other areas that are included
in the um document on role playing and
simulated patient experience. I I
believe and um correct me, but that says
either 5 to 10 or 10 hours. So I think
some of them are are in rules but I I
think they're also guidance. I mean the
end of life particular we only have four
indications right now. We'd hope that a
program would provide you know a good
good amount of teaching in those in that
area. So so guidance but I think if a
program is going to be approved it
should be covering these areas.
>> Thank you Larry. Um, Denali,
>> hi. Um, just to add to that, I think
part of the subcommittee's um, desire
for minimum hours in certain content
areas also came from the department's
position that there can't be special
like we can't have uh, a paliative care
requirement for um, end of life
practitioners. Um, same with PTSD,
right? There's there's the position is
that there can't be specific
requirements for specific indications.
And I think that that emphasizes the
need because we we know that
particularly those two um qualifying
conditions, end of life and PTSD. Um
there there just is clinically a a big
need for specialized education. Um, I'
I'd really recommend that it doesn't
have to be these minimum hours, but
there be uh, you know, some minimum
standard for for trauma, PTSD, and um,
and end of life.
>> Thank you, Denali. Greg,
>> thank you, Denali. just to make sure
that I heard you correctly and um to say
say that back to you, the department is
saying that at this time that we can't
quite have like specification or
psychedelic majors or anything like
that. So the idea is to make sure the
categories and subject matter is covered
in a requirement for programs to have.
And I think that maybe if that's the
case, we can even shift the language to
condition specific or condition
specification.
So coverage like broad coverage because
rapidly in the next year, we're going to
start adding new conditions. So as that
happens, I think creating the language
and the recommendation to cover for
future proofing uh shifts in the scope
of care might be wise here.
Is that correct? Is did I hear that from
you correctly, Denelli?
>> Yeah. Yeah, that's um so there was a
recommendation from I think this came
out of end of life that their committee
there was a recommendation to have you
know special um training requirements
for people who are providing end of life
care. I think the position from the
department was that that's not possible
under the rules and so the the shift at
least for those indications. I think
there's some other things that we may
want there to be minimum hours for, but
um specifically the trauma and end of
life minimum hours came as a response to
um to that position from the department.
>> Thank you. Uh uh who's next? Um
uh I think it's Ann. Oh, Desba. Okay.
>> Yes.
>> Go ahead. Go ahead, Desba. Hi, good
morning. Um, just not to derail
everything, just using licensed u
massage therapy as a as an example, you
know, we have I think four hours of
ethics that we um we have to pro, you
know, show proof of of training for that
for our continuing education. To me,
that seems like that would fall in the
line of like the [clears throat] end of
life care. Not to diminish the idea of
having a specified
uh uh training for something, but you
know there's I think that's partially
the reason for the broad broad uh
overview of like what would fall under
these particular categories. And so in
the language it would probably be you
know for example end of life care that's
specified for this thing would fall
under say ethics. And when you're going
to uh you know work or practice in these
particular areas you know I can't say
that I'm a myofascial release uh uh body
worker unless I've actually had like the
certification and show and indicate that
I have received this. So I think this is
an opportunity too for those particular
places to say you know this person is
certified in end of life care and other
um entities other schools other training
that is like this is specifically what
we're doing and we can provide the end
of life care certific certification that
would be uh fulfilling say for instance
an ethics uh requirement that the uh
state offers. I'm not saying that this
is what should be put to practice or I'm
disregarding any other conversations
that we've had that I have not uh been
privy to, but I'm just, you know, there
I think that's the reason for these
broad um categories is so that other
things could potentially fall into those
things and then understanding what
that's like. Um I mean how how do we
fulfill those particular requirements
that are so broadly uh spectrum for the
rest of the state could be even for
traditional language uh traditional
knowledge um and so forth but that was
just an example.
Thank you.
>> Thank you Despa. Uh next we have is that
um for some reason I can't really see.
>> Go ahead. It's a Okay. Thank you.
>> Hi everyone. Um, you know, having a lot
a large uh role in coming up with these
recommendations, I did actually intend
these to be specific requirements that
educational training programs are going
to need to document somehow in their
application. I I think that um, you
know, this is how it works in Oregon.
This is how it works in Colorado and
likely other state programs will require
that, too. Um, and I think that, you
know, there is a great deal of
flexibility within this, but I think
it's going to be really important for
the credibility of the program and the
credibility of the, you know, of the
DO's program to ensure that these
educational training programs actually
are teaching to these hours. And so I
would imagine that when teaching when
schools apply, they're going to need to
do a curriculum crosswalk that shows,
you know, this is how we meet this hour.
this is how we meet these hours. Um, and
it's really, you know, I like the idea
of it being flexible and I think there's
a lot of flexibility in this, but I
think we also really need to maintain
high standards to ensure that programs
are training competent clinicians who
are prepared to work across a variety of
conditions. Um so I would say
uh these offer a lot of flexibility but
I do think that these need to be things
that programs should document and that
these minimum hours really I think are a
matter are are really a safety
protection for the public for the
program and also for the department of
health.
>> Thank you an
um well I have a question for Dominic.
Um I I think Dominic uh you and I and
Larry we we talked about um this that if
you know if we're putting a lot in here
that it could potentially be um
a a lot more than than we
[clears throat] anticipated. So I I
think we we did we did talk about that,
didn't we, Dominic?
Um, we did talk about uh I mean a
variety of different things and but I'm
not sure what you mean about having too
much in here.
>> Right. Right. And so if this is really
broad I think we have to kind of start
with something but if we're um I think
my understanding was that we were going
to have that um if we were going to put
a lot more
um I guess information in some of these
modules that uh you know if we're trying
to add something on later on that uh it
would be maybe to uh
uh starting off with just the the
minimum things that maybe we could add
on more uh information into some of
these modules that it could be probably
potentially get too big. Is is that what
my understanding was on this?
>> I I mean it
I'm not really I'm still not really
under sure that I understand. I mean as
the program continues to develop and
this is the part the other aspect of it
as additional conditions are added in
things like that that then we'd need to
be adding in with the rules we would
need to add in items such as um you know
say uh for example uh Dr. Leman has uh
presented that we should be adding a
major depressive disorder. And so if we
did that then what would end up
happening is how many hours then in this
training would need to go in there. We
would have to then modify the
regulations for that. And so and and by
the way that's just as an example. So as
additional conditions get added, we
would then have to add in specificity if
the rules were written in this way to
add in all of those items. And then the
question would come at that point and
this would come to the board and to this
committee of well if we are shifting
these hours around somewhat. What areas
are we taking away from that we said
originally needed to have these kinds of
specific hours and what kinds of areas
you know how many hours are we adding
into the dactic um in addition to this
original baseline. So yes that could
cause a problem. Now one thing that with
this is there are and just to note
because uh in the earlier page and I
don't think it's been spoken about
previously yet in the earlier page it
does say the daki is at 80 hours and
here it says the total specified
minimums are at 63. So that does give 17
hours of a little leeway to add some of
those things in. But there is that
possibility that if enough conditions
get added, if there are enough different
items that as the evaluations come in
that we need to add additional topic
areas that it could exceed that 80 hours
and we would at that point have to
revisit because they're not specified
here in there. Now, one of the other
aspects of this and and I think this is
a part that you know uh has been touched
on by several different people speaking
is
regardless of what ends up in the rules
in the final version is there does have
to be a crosswalk with any of the
programs that are doing this when they
apply to be an educational program.
They'll have to submit their curriculum
to ensure that they're covering all of
the topics that they have the
appropriate amount of education in the
different areas. And that's really where
specific hours really comes in is as
they're submitting that to the
department and as we review that
curricula, are they covering all of
those hours in an appropriate way with
their syllabi and with their actual
proposed curriculum. So that's kind of
where that difference happens. And I
think some of what sort of is kind of
happening is everybody's thinking we
have to put all of the specifics into
the rule, but um that's that's not
actually the case. And that's why we
recommend for the rule it not have the
specific number of hours because of
changes in that happening. It helps to
allow for greater flexibility as the
program continues to develop. And for
the educational programs,
Thank you, Dominic. I know I I was kind
of stubbling on trying to to um you
know, uh get the the question out here
because Yeah. Um thank you for
explaining that.
>> Uh who do we have next here? Um
>> Larry, go ahead, Dr. Leman.
>> Oh,
>> yeah. Thank you. Just a couple of
comments. One on the like as we're
adding new conditions and such. those
seem great for like the continuing
education hours that are going to be
required. I could see like a a module
being developed on generalized anxiety
disorder different things. So it isn't
like you get a like in any kind of a you
know a health care profession isn't like
you get trained and you're done. So we
should keep that in mind for some of
those other areas as well. I I'd be
interested if people are there any of
these areas that people seem excessive.
What we what we tried to do is we looked
at like the 150 and 130 in um Oregon and
really tried to see what we thought was
sort of a bare minimum and and you know
so that that was a little bit where
these numbers came from like you know
we're treating people with depression
people have and so screening suicidality
seemed important. It also came back that
people in Colorado recommended more
hours than that. Um a lot of this is
pretty basic prep integration
administration. So although I do
appreciate the concern about being too
too constraining, I think most of these
are pretty core management of
challenging experiences. Um you know I
think when you look through they all
seem like I I'm having trouble picturing
a good training that doesn't talk about
prep, integration, administration,
suicidality, trauma, end of life. So
just to put a pitch in for that the
numbers are were really designed to be a
minimum.
>> Thank you, Larry.
Go ahead, Denali.
>> Yeah. Um, uh, grateful for the
opportunity to explore this more. I'm
just looking at the the time and
thinking, um, you know, if our goal is
as a committee to make recommendations,
um, wanting to make sure that we have an
opportunity to see what this side by
side is from the department. Um I know
some folks in the subcommittee have but
um just was going to make a request to
view Brenda if we can um be sure that
there's an opportunity to
um both hear from the department with
enough time for discussion since they're
going to need our feedback by um before
uh Tuesday when they plan to publish.
>> Okay. I could see if we could um get us
together to do that. Um I can
um try to pull something together
probably. So it's it'll be this Tuesday.
So maybe trying to meet on um Sunday or
Monday. Uh we could try to do that.
>> I I think Denali just said to that and
forgive me Denali if I'm presuming on
this but just to see if in this meeting
we can go ahead and show that side by
side and I'm happy to do so. um we do
have that available as far as for uh the
hours sort of set up with regard to the
practicum. Really on the dactic side,
quite frankly, we're not really very
different. So, I I'm not worried. It's
just really comes down to the questions
of items like what we're just discussing
now as far as putting specific numbers
in because the topic areas while they're
spelled out a little differently and
include from multiple curricula from
different organizations both in Colorado
or uh Oregon and some of the ones in New
Mexico. Um they're really they cover the
same topics. It's just a question of do
we put the hour specific in or not. So
>> yeah, my apologies. I misunderstood.
Thank you.
>> Chris Caldwell, go ahead.
>> Hi all. Um, I had to hop off for 20
minutes, so I'll apologize if this
question was already answered, but I am
curious since there aren't any of the
current uh training organizations in
Colorado or Oregon who include end of
life pali of care considerations.
Then if you're offering reciproc
reciprocity
um, but nobody is getting the end of
life care training, how is that going to
work?
Colorado does not require eight hours.
I mean, I teach classes for Colorado.
>> Larry, you want to answer that?
>> Yeah. Oh, well I mean it may be a better
question for Don, but I you know and I
think this will become clear as we look
on the practicum like we're recommending
a practicum that has a certain number of
of sessions. Um but my understanding is
that with the reciprocity people will be
approved if they have the practicum that
they're currently is required in
Colorado. So I I don't think there's
going to be a a perfect match between
the reciprocity and what we're
requiring. I think particularly you'll
see in practicum I think that we have
more than um people who've gone through
those programs but so I would refer that
question to Dom but that that would be
that would be one thought on it.
>> Yeah actually it does create an issue um
and uh and it is a great point with
regard to it. So, thank you for bringing
it up. Um, because it does require the
reciprocity still requires a crosswalk
showing that the curriculum meets the
needs of the the program that will be in
the rules. So, if you do specify the
number of hours, it does create a
problem for some of those reciprocities
um that may not necessarily be specific
um you know have such things
specifically. And so that's also a
little bit of a difference in why we
don't recommend in the the rules
themselves to put that kind of
specificity for each topic because they
do have to provide a crosswalk showing
that all topics are covered. So that
would create an issue there.
>> Yeah. Because
I think your mic was cut off.
>> Was Chris cut off? Can we hear what she
was saying?
>> Sorry, Chris. Yeah. Um, sorry about
that.
>> Yeah, no worries. Um, yeah. So, since I
do teach a class for Changa Institute,
um, so to Ann's comment earlier, it's a
two-hour class I teach and there's a 45
minute like homework
Yeah, I think if it's okay like
>> pulling from memory. Yeah, thanks.
Pulling from memory along the lines of
reciprocity. If say you took a course
that was 2 hours in Colorado and the
requirement if we have a set requirement
that that
um those hours are met at 8 hours then
you may need to supplement your
educational requirement to meet the
standards of this program.
I don't think that reciprocity is
intended
>> here. And I think we're drifting far
from our needed topic today, but I think
it's interesting how
reciprocity doesn't mean
uh cart launch I think is what Desba
referred to. The reason I raised rose my
hand was to call out uh Denali's
intention to cover the rules draft
today. And I think my uh in support of
that, the question to the department is
do you already have the rules draft
prepped? And if not, um I'm happy to
like help diff that in like a diet like
whenever that's ready,
whoever gets to see it to compare it. Um
I'm going to do that anyway. So I'm
happy to support that effort.
>> Thank you, Greg.
Dr. Leman, go ahead.
>> Yeah, a couple just a couple of
thoughts. One is hearing that Chang is
only having two hours on end of life to
me is a really good argument for having
a minimum of higher than that and that
that gets people to be doing what we're
covering in our state, which is end of
life is one of four diagnoses. So, I
consider that to be almost an argument
for having minimum numbers. I I do want
to try to figure out how we're going to
deal with this when we get into the
practicum. Um, you know, Dom, do and I I
agree really has wanted there to be more
practicum in New Mexico than in Colorado
or Oregon. So, by doing that, we're
almost setting up that the people that
have gotten those trainings that we want
to give reciprocity to won't meet those
those requirements. I at one point I
thought we had concluded that during the
reciprocity period we would accept um a
lesser amount of practicum, but I just
wanted to raise that issue. And I also
realize I'm jumping ahead because we
haven't talked about practicing.
>> Okay. Well, maybe this will be a good
time to [clears throat] do that. Oh, um
Jeff,
>> thank you. Good morning everybody.
Sorry, I just jumped on my call. Um you
know something that I saw other states
were doing and forgive if you've already
talked about this. I was just trying to
look at the list of topics there online
on my own, but uh is there going to be
any training for postjourney
difficulties? I'm specifically referring
to hallucinogen persisting perception
disorder where people have long-asting
visual effects
uh negative visual effects or but uh you
know there there there's actually I
don't know if that you call it
established treatments for this but
people are being treated for it and I
think in New Mexico there's going to be
small number of people who are going to
have it and uh It'd be good if people
are trained on it and we have a protocol
and a place to send them and so this
training committee is a good one to talk
about that I would think in part. So I
just want to put that on folks radars
and see what we're thinking about that.
>> Thank you for that. Um we there will be
a continuum of care afterwards and um
that's a very good question. So I think
when when someone is experiencing
something that was caused by
uh a treatment uh the continuum of care
uh to follow up uh afterwards uh we did
talk about that um and I think that um
we're there is something but we haven't
really talked about it in length.
>> Sure. Brenda, there's an article I'll
send you from Scientific American about
a new clinic that just opened up dealing
with this. Maybe it would be helpful to
have them even be a speaker at one of
your committee meetings. Uh just to
learn about because it's it's all pretty
new um as are these legal treatments and
uh we can learn about it and then see
what our thoughts are, how we can
integrate ourselves.
>> Yeah. Uh there, you know, there's
there's all kinds of things that happen
with marijuana, too. There um I don't
know what the um actual diagnosis is,
but people that suffer from um you know,
having too much marijuana and then they
can't do it anymore because uh you know,
I I don't know what the medical term for
this diagnosis is, but uh it's it's
life-threatening.
uh it's so uh um I had a client with
that and uh so it does require um
afterare and med uh you know uh careful
uh avoidance of any cannabis products
for an individual with that. But yeah,
um yeah, I would like to see that
article um and and talk about that in
length more about what to do uh for
people that have persistent um like
psychosis or hallucin
hallucinations
uh after a treatment. Um I think um
that's where the
um physical comes in for the diagnostic
uh physician uh to give a clearance. But
then again, there's no telling uh when
it comes to the mind how people are
going to react to it. And yeah, it's it
seems to be a fairly rare condition, but
it can happen. And especially if people
already have a a family history of
psychosis and schizophrenia, there's a
possibility from what I know from
reading uh a little bit about this. But
yeah, thank you very much. I think this
would be a really good thing to um uh
put in in the education and training
part as a a followup um as uh people are
being treated that this could possibly
potentially happen.
>> Yeah.
>> I mean it's it's one of the few adverse
serious adverse things but but there you
have it. And so if we're since we're
starting a a program at scale in a
sense, it would be good to
to have it on our uh have it at our our
work. Thank you, Brenda. A link to that.
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah, I'll try to post it in the chat
soon. Thanks,
>> Brenda. Uh Ann Mets has a comment.
>> Go ahead.
>> Hi, just Hi, everyone. Um, you know,
also just um echoing what Denali and uh
doc and Larry have said about wanting to
move on to the sidebyside comparison.
Um, and also just a brief consideration
for including hours in the regulations.
Um, you know, I think if we don't have
an hour's minimum, you could imagine a
program being 70 hours of content on
astral projection and 10 hours on things
related to psilocybin therapy and having
a program like that apply. The do I
imagine would reject it, but they don't
have objective criteria with which they
would need to do that. And I think just
as a protection from somebody who runs a
program, I think it's really important
that programs are offered concrete
numbers about what they need to be in
compliance. Um, you know, in Colorado
that's really helpful for us at Fluence
just to be able to say like, okay, do we
have enough? You know, we have six hours
of end of life. Is that in compliance
with what Colorado is requiring? We have
10 hours of self-care. Is that enough?
Um, so I think from program standpoint,
it's really important to include
specific hours. Um, and also for the DO
to be able to make objective decisions.
>> Thank you.
Next.
So, yeah, I think I'm going to walk back
a little bit from my earlier position.
Um, [clears throat] and kind of
Oh, you got disconnected, Greg.
>> Is this how computers work?
>> Yeah, I think so.
>> Sorry.
[laughter]
>> Oh, you did it on purpose. Oh,
>> not completely. shut him up. [laughter]
>> Um I think just walking back my
positioning on on ambiguous hours and
whatnot. Um,
I'm wondering if it's possible
considering that it is going to be a
rapidly shifting landscape to have the
categories or the types of things
written into the rules and have the
rules point to guidance documents where
that gives the committee and the
department the power to shift and adjust
these where when the department is
reviewing an application, they have
concrete minimum hours that they can
refer to, but we're not locked into that
um number
having to be uh passed through a rules
hearing to adjust. is that so I either
write it directly into the rules as as
we're proposing or create the if then
um
sit scenario that allows us to have
uh progressive flexibility. I think
that's
a a or b might be where I'm at on that.
Yeah, I I like what you're saying, Greg.
um that uh if we have something like
that that that would make it um more
flexible and um having it uh
in in the document. But then, you know,
I think keeping it the way um we need to
have it so we can make these changes is
going to um make this program um more uh
uh have more
I'm I'm losing my words here. Um but
make it more flexible. I guess that's
what I'm trying to say. Um, so, uh, do
we want to move on to the next, um, part
of this? Thank you, Desba. That's the
word I was looking for. Robust. Thank
you.
Because I want to give us plenty of time
to move on to um, you know, the other
side by side here that we have here.
Okay. So uh the specified minimum
account for 63 of the 80 hours.
This is the uh training and education uh
the committee. This is what we we're
doing here. The remaining 17 hours are
devoted to the topics. The rule requires
without an hour minimum an overview of
licensed provider facilitator
responsibilities including how to work
as part of a care team and the unique
role of nonclinical peer support
facilitators and treatment models. The
model concludes with an evaluation
demonstrating competency across all
areas. A note on the trauma minimum. 7
hours is not PTSD treatment training and
should not be represented as such. It
prepares trainees to recognize
disassociation and trauma responses.
Work somatically and deescalate. Where
PTSD treatment falls outside a provider
scope, collaboration with a PTSD trained
provider is the appropriate path. So,
we're looking at, you know, specific
training here to make sure that we're
the patients that we're working at are
are getting qualified, trained
clinicians that can help with these with
with trauma. So, this is pretty
important because this is touching on
what we were talking about earlier about
specific training. Uh, does anybody have
any comments or um uh questions about
this?
Okay, I think we can move on to the
next. Okay.
All righty. So um before applying for
certification, licensed providers and
facilitators also hold current emergency
response credentials, basic life support
or both CPR or AED certification or New
Mexico EMT lensure or clinical uh
license that includes these
competencies.
The practicum and supervised practice uh
the 102 to 114 supervised hours.
Supervised practice is se sequenced from
lower risk to higher risk experience and
no one completes it without real client
contact. That's very important. Um
facilitators track students complete a
total of 102 practicum hours licensed
and I'll let Dominic post that.
Okay. and uh license provider track in
as students complete 114.
So here um in the stage uh practicum
super um the well participants
24 hours uh training potential
compensate is there's no compensation.
Um and then the client medicine sessions
are two and this is for the practicum
supervised onsite 72 hours for licensed
provider 62 for facilitator. So uh the
participant without qualifying or risk
heightening condition complete before
seeing patients with qualifying
conditions include preparation and
administration and integration.
Uh two co-f facilitator 24 minimum
hours. There's uh for the traininee um
there is no compensation
uh client medicine sessions is two co-ac
co-f facilitator with a do permitted
licensed provider low acuity patients
such as nicotine use disorder or
depression includes preparation
administration and integration.
Um three, stage three the work group
work which is 12 uh potentially there is
compet uh compensation
client medicine sessions one group of
preparation administration and
integration
and four provider supervisor supervisory
hours uh LP track only that's a minimum
of 12 and the traininee uh potential
compensation
Possibly yes and client medicine
sessions is one co-f facilitating with
per permitted facilitator for
administration of same day therapy
sessions. So that's a supervisor uh
practice case consulted consultation 42
hours licensed provider of facilitator.
Okay, moving on. Uh number five
supervised with practice case
consultation.
Okay, that's 42 to 24 plus or 18 hours
potential compensation. Yes. And then
two, as far as um uh the hours needed is
training complete 24 hours of supervised
practice with a permitted licensed
provider for two clients designated by
the hosting school or healing center
which may include people with end of
life complex PTSD or opioid addiction as
qualifying conditions. The 24 hours are
12 hours with each participant and
eight-hour medicine day, two 60-minute
preparation sessions, and two 60-inute
integration sessions. Both clients are
presented and discussed within an
18-hour consultation group. And this
stage may occur in the 2-year period
after the individual has received their
training licenses. The total licensed
practitioner is 114 hours. the
facilitators 102 and then there is uh
the eight and eight um client medicine
sessions in total for four of them
before compensation may occur
okay is that uh we have more
okay um every stage I'll wait well we'll
wait for that to get posted every stage
spans preparation administration
integration not administration alone
Students begin with well participants
before seeing patients with qualifying
conditions then to to move co-f
facilitation with the department permit
license provider. Licensed provider
tracks students additionally complete
supervisory hours building the skills
the role requires. hours in co-f
facilitation group work and
participation supervision may be earned
simultaneously with each actual hour
counting only once towards 102 and 114
aggregate. Any remaining balance is
completed through co-f facilitation
designated by the hosting school or
healing center. Once a student has
completed at least 48 hours practicum,
the end of life uh stage two, they are
qualified to care to high acuity
patients with accompanied by a licensed
provider graduated on a ramp that
expands what a student can do as
demonstrator experience accumulate uh
accumulates. All pra p p p p p p p p p p
p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p p
p p p p p p p p p practicum hours take
place in approved healing center or
other approved location and supervisors
and students follow the program's
facilitation and therapy rules, HIPPA
and high-tech confidentially
requirements and application scope of
practicum limits.
Okay, let's continue on.
uh practicum case uh presentation and
consultation competency checkpoint. As
part of the case presentation and
consultation, every student participates
in at least 18 hours of case
presentation and consultation with
education program facility which program
may provide through contact contract
with third party. During these hours,
each student presents at least two cases
in which they personally provide direct
psilocybin services which contribute to
another 24 hours training hour
presentations and consultation include
discussion of an individual case
concerns, risk factors, supportive
factors, treatment considerations and
recommendations for afterare. A full
case conceptualization,
not a formality. The two case
presentations must be completed before
lensure. This is the piece that makes
the overall hour requirements defensible
rather than relying on raw hour counts.
Someone experienced evaluates the new
provider's actual casework before
independent practice. The 18 hours
remain valid up to 12 months after a
practicum is completed. The model
mirrors the consultation structure
developed at um Memorial Memorial
in Boulder under the leadership of one
of the leading principal investigation
in MAPS MDMA clinical trials. Okay. Saw
that Ann had your hand up. Ann.
Yes. Um, so this is really an
improvement I think on what both Oregon
and Colorado are doing to ensure that
the final sort of final stage of a
training for a new clinician is that
they really have some sign off by
someone who is experienced. And um,
obviously Colorado has a 40-hour
consultation model. Um, but there's not
a whole lot of regulation around what
that looks like. The exception to that
of course is the Mearoo model where they
require uh people who've completed their
practicum hours to be part of a regular
ongoing consultation group where they
share two cases um but they also present
and give feedback and share and I think
the value of this is that it really
creates um you know kind of a model for
interprofessional collaboration um for
sort of working with other clinicians
and It also is a gatekeeping strategy of
just ensuring that um we're not putting
clinicians out in out to work in the
public on their own independently
without having someone who's um you know
competent and has been working in the
field signing off on their clinical
skills. So I think um you know sometimes
a critique of training programs is that
for psychedelics it's paytoplay and this
is really I think a wonderful way of
ensuring that people who complete the uh
recommendations and the didactic and the
practical experience are qualified to be
out there that they're the sort of
clinicians that we would be fine
treating our parents our grandparents
our children. So, I hope people uh
consider this and just think of this as
a really great but innovative way to go
ahead. I know the DO has proposed a
10-hour postcertification
um mentorship. Uh I my concern with
postcertification is that there's not
really any sort of um leverage to ensure
that people actually do that if people
already have their certification. So I
think this is a a better approach just
to make sure that people are having uh
professional eyes on at the very last
minute.
Thank you an
um uh let's see let's continue on.
Okay. All righty. I see Gregory,
>> just really quick, not to get too deep
into it, but put to put a pin in this
thought. Um, the I love the memory
model. I super inspired and um, uh,
excited to hear that Dr. Leman and Dr.
Matz were able to meet with them in
Boulder. Um, I wonder if there's a way
down the line to create um
CE credits for participating in
uh something like this, like not all
your CE, but maybe um as an incentive to
get people to be constantly in
conversation and on the leading edge of
understanding.
um should have value um down the road. I
think you know we need to stand
something up before we get into that
conversation. But um I'm glad to see
this in here. Thank you, Ann.
>> Thank you, Greg.
>> Okay. Um so here we have a comparison of
ours between Colorado and New Mexico. Uh
here we have in the didactic Colorado
150, New Mexico's 80. Uh practicum and
case presentations. Colorado's 40 and
New Mexico's 114 for the licensed
practitioner, 102 for the facilitator.
Uh Colorado's consultation, um no
medical sessions required. So that is 40
hours where New Mexico we we don't have
that. um psilocybin uh med medicine
sessions and training Colorado's two and
New Mexico's eight or four before
compensation may occur and then the
total hours we have for Colorado is 230
and New Mexico here we have between you
know for the licensed practitioner I'm
sorry uh 194 and then the facilitator is
okay yeah um uh it says here. Uh, can we
skip the read through in the next part?
Uh, so maybe uh Dr. Leman or Dr. Mets
can give a short summary. Yes. Um, I
think that's a good suggestion, Denali.
Um, yes, that's uh would any of you Dr.
Leman or Dr. formats would like to um uh
elaborate on or summarize uh the latter
part of uh what we're trying to hear
just to save some time so we can get to
the the do
>> if I may suggest um these these two
areas actually do not differ at all
between uh either proposal.
So I would just suggest that uh if we
move forward because people do want to
see the comparisons
um because neither of these change um
and essentially what they really are if
it's okay is continuing education
certifying clinicians have eight hours
and then the providers facilitators 20
hours each of continuing ed every two
years. Um and then the records have to
be kept for five years which includes uh
basically the syllabi enrollment etc. Uh
and then um you know uh the the
practicum what exactly happens during
practicum sessions number of people etc.
Um and then the transition pathway is
that uh it's essentially they would have
to the programs would have to uh show a
walkth through uh that demonstrates that
the program they went through elsewhere
meets the dactic requirements um and
that they just have to have a practicum
of 40 documented count uh contact hours
including a minimum of the two
individual and group sessions. um and
that that allows for people to be able
to come in uh from from other programs
who've already been trained and that
actually does not differ between the
two.
>> All righty. Uh yeah. Uh let's go ahead
and uh move forward with that, Dominic.
I I agree.
So, um, just because of from a timing
standpoint, what I'm I'm going to do
here is, um, I'm just going to, and
pardon me, I'm trying to get this this
new file or this other file rather, to
display. Uh, so give me just a moment.
Okay. Are people able to see it? It's
showing oddly on my screen and I just
want to make sure people can see.
>> Yeah, if we could blow it up a little
bit more.
>> Yeah. Yeah. I just wanted to make sure
people could see it first.
>> Okay,
there we go.
>> Um, and give me just a moment to make a
few more adjustments. There we go. That
should
Okay. Um, and so what this does is this
really just shows the comparison between
the two. Oh, uh, pardon me. Let me get
this into the chat for everybody.
Uh okay. And um so basically uh when we
run and we look at the com the two
different aspects side by side again
they're very similar at this point in
time. they are organized a little bit
differently between the two but um you
know and except for even though we've
had the conversations about specificity
of ours you know I think the topics are
you know uh are and the competency areas
as I mentioned before we really took
them not just from this proposal but
also from others that had been submitted
uh as far as um examples of other uh and
different um uh educational programs
from other places as well including
Colorado, Oregon, um Odyssey for example
and a few other places and just to
ensure that the different content areas
are included. So I've put that as far as
content areas and I apologize on the
formatting. It doesn't like how it uh uh
how it's formatted in I put that on into
the chat just for the topic areas so
people can see them. Um but what we
really have is if you look here the
prerequisites and other requirements are
actually the same across the board. So
whether it's the proposed the this
alternative proposed rule from um the
training and education or what do is
proposing it's actually the same uh as
far as for all of these prerequisites
and the other requirements including the
HIPPO privacy the New Mexico module and
the emergency response aspect. Um and uh
so the first aspect on the didactic
again for the the certifying clinician
it is the same so I won't dwell on that.
Um and then the only real difference
between the provider and practitioner
aspect oh and forgive me this should
have been um or I'm sorry yes between
the provider practitioner and then the
facilitators is really just how they get
proportioned a little bit within the
general modules. So in the proposed
rule, it's 78 hours within those general
topic areas and then two hours of
simulated patient. For the practitioner
under the DO proposed rule, it's 65
hours under the general module. And then
there's an additional five hours that um
that are specific for those providers,
for the practitioners. Um and I'm just
going to use the term licensed provider
just because that's what's being used
here. So but that's the same category.
Um and so there's the additional five
hours. So that's 70 hours total. And
then there's 10 hours of simulated
patient requirement. Now just to be
clear what 10 hours is required in this.
It is just a minimum of 10 hours of
simulation role play those sort of
things throughout the various portions
of the the training. They don't
necessarily need to be done as a block.
We just want to ensure that as people
are going through the training, they are
getting that experience without meeting
with patients first. So in a simulated
way that they're going through and
walking through the different aspects.
Um and then for a facilitator, it's
exactly the same. Uh again on the uh
training and education proposal 78 hours
for the module so the dactic and two
hours unsimulated and for the
facilitator in the do version it is just
65 hours in those modules five hours
that are specific to the facilitators
um and training that they would need
since the roles are a little different
and then again 10 hours on the simulated
patient. Um, so the overall didactic
with regard to Bolt, including all of
the simulated patient and role play is
really 80 hours. So again, as we've kind
of said, it's really not very different.
Um, it's very, very similar, a little
bit difference in how it should be
presented within the rules, but really
overall the dactic hours. And if you
look and compare the the different areas
of competency, you'll see they align
very well, just outlined a little bit
differently.
Um, and then the Well, and I should just
say, are there questions at this point?
And Larry, you have your hand raised. Go
ahead.
>> Thanks, Dom. I'm going to kind of switch
sides on this one here. Um, I've been
advocating for more specific hours and
you for less, but I think with the um,
uh, simulated patient requirement, I I
would encourage, you know, doing more
like five or six just for the thing that
you talked about just to maintain some
flexibility. Um, because if we put 10
hours in there, we we basically have
taken away most of the the other ones
that we were encouraging as electives.
So I I would encourage the idea of 6
hours and I could see that being
something like um three three hours um
on ex you know exercises or practice and
then three hours on some type of
simulation but I just want to throw that
out perhaps shortening that.
>> Thank you.
>> Okay, not seeing anything else. I'll go
ahead and I'll move forward to the
practicum. Um and so again I'm here um
and uh and again the what we really have
is for the well patients um the uh the
alternative side uh from the education
committee is 24 hours with well patients
and students. um we do not have that
aspect in the do and the main reason why
we do not is with the current statute.
We are not able to do it with
individuals who do not have one of the
qualifying conditions. Um and uh so then
the next stage is patients with low
acuity on that aspect. There's 24 in the
alternative proposal and 20 hours with
regard to um on the DO proposal. And
then really the next portion which is
the general practicum have it listed is
it's really again about how structured
in the different charts and proposals uh
for the most part and so the way it's
structured in the do is that the general
practicum really has six individual
patients in two groups. It doesn't split
that on up and that's really about how
many hours really with regard to same
day administration sessions. Now again
that's a minimum. So we realize in some
cases to achieve those hours individuals
may end up having additional sessions
that they are in. Um but we leave that
up to them whether they're individual or
groups. And then we do specify that
there need to be at least uh 20 hours
with regard to preparatory and
integrative sessions. it doesn't split
it out into the different areas because
and and this actually came up in the
equity committee meeting is depending on
the patient there may be a different
number of preparatory or integration
sessions and so we want to ensure that
there's flexibility there but that it
does need to be with six individuals and
at least a minimum of one group. Now,
part of the guidance on this, and this
is not a part of the rule because this
does go into the guidance documents that
accompany all of this, um, is that it
really should be with the same patients.
So, for example, in the general, the six
individuals that should really carry
forward or backwards depending on which
part of the time, and that they be the
same individuals for the preparatory and
integrative sessions. However, we don't
want to keep that necessarily and and
require that in the rule because there
could be a lot of situations where, for
example, um one of the students is sick
and so they miss a preparatory session
and so that would then create additional
logistical problems if we required that
they had to be exactly the same patients
throughout. Now the best practice would
be is that they are the same patients
with potentially some additional
sessions that they attend but we don't
want to create that kind of a burden for
individuals and so that's why uh it is
it should be through and the guidance
will be that it should be the same
individuals but there may be cases where
a particular say student facilitator
misses an integrative session or the
patient says I would actually prefer
this to be just between myself and the
practitioner the provider or you know
some other sort of scenario and so
that's why we don't specify that part
within the rule but it will be a part of
the guidance on it. Um and then just the
it's very similar with regard to that is
the um the group work uh having been set
up in that way along with the patients
in low acuity on the training and
educational side and so it's very
similar in that way. Um and then really
the the next part is and and I think
this is a little bit different in how it
was just presented on it um is uh that
the supervised practicum uh which is the
only difference between the facilitators
and the providers aspect of it is the um
the supervised practicum is actually
where a a student who is going to be a
provider is supervising the the
administr ation day portion and the
integration and um preparatory sessions
with the facilitators also being present
doing their work as well. And so that's
actually what the supervision practicum
in the DO presentation is. And the
reason for that is because the way the
statute being written that the
individuals who are doing this must be
licensed that this is the way to allow
for facilitators to be able to
participate and be a part of this
without necessarily having a separate
lensure other than the certification
through here. Oh, and I'm apologize I
did skip a line the by accident the case
presentation and consultation in both
cases it is two cases. on the the
training and education presentation they
separated those hours out what we just
do is we have that from the do proposal
have it included in those practicum
hours so that is a part of that that
between the gener general practicum and
the preparatory so that 80 hours total
that's just included in there and it
does involve that they would have to do
that presentation with regard to two
cases so that they have that experience
and then of course in both situations
and and proposals they get um evaluated
and that those students have to pass
those evaluations. So in the total what
the total practicum hours end up being
is uh 120 for the provider side and 100
for the u the facilitators and then
after graduation the continuing
education is the same as we noted before
across the board um with the exception
of course is that it's eight hours of
CME for the clinicians aspect of it and
then what we did add is um the
department does have that aspect in the
proposal of the mentorship hours and
those are something that um that the the
educational programs will have to
provide. they'll be required to provide
it. And that is that area where a recent
graduate would be able to reach out to
be able to have some of that supervision
and some of that mentorship to consult
with other participants or I'm sorry
with other providers and facilitators in
cases that they may have. And so that
they would be required to do that and
that would be over a year period. Then
after that it is up to them to determine
if they would like to continue that. But
we are saying that that has to be a part
of whatever fees it ends up being or uh
cost to uh a student who is going
through this program. So those 10 hours
cannot have an additional cost added on.
Um and really in a nutshell that fits
with that comparison. Now the one other
thing because people did bring it on up
is um and and I think it's a really
great aspect of it and uh when it was
brought up and I apologize I don't
remember who did in one of the previous
meetings is we did add in the aspect
that when students are going through
their practicum once they have completed
50 hours of the practicum they then
could be in that uh that paid sort of
level on it. And so as long once they
have finished half of the practicum,
then they would be able to also be a
part of that billing and that payment
structure and also get paid themselves
for during that practicum. So that's
halfway through the practicum for the
the 100 base hours. I hope that helps
and makes sense.
>> Thank you, Dominic. Uh so at this point
in time, we do have some time here. Um,
uh, are we finished? Yeah, we're
finished. Um, so does anyone else have,
uh, any comments, suggestions, or
questions at this point in time.
Denali,
thanks. Um, just two really quick
thoughts. Um, and I know that I've
shared this already, the um, I I think
the two group requirement that um the
department is proposing I I'm really
glad that we're focused on group. I
think it's a great model for cost and
other reasons um and for peer
involvement. And um I'm I worry about
the ability of training programs who are
in more rural communities um to be able
to to execute too. So I'd love to see
that drop to one. Um and then the
mentorship piece I I think that what we
want from that from training programs we
actually get through the case
presentation and consultation. Um right
we want people to be able to have that
feedback um from licensed providers
um on actual uh patient experience. And
so I think because the department has
integrated the case presentation and
consultation um there's an ability to to
wrap that u mentoring
have have that um fulfilled um
in there. So I would recommend that we
remove the 10-hour mentoring.
Thank you Denali. Um so
at this point um how does the department
uh Dominic feel about removing that 10
hours?
>> Uh again I think that's off topic on
this at this time. So I would suggest
that we stick on this because there's
only about uh what do we have about 20
minutes remaining. So I would say we
need to stay on topic
>> with regard to that and that's something
uh that really was within the end of
life meeting not here.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> And and just to sort of respond since
there's there's not other people. The
reason we added in the mentoring was
actually on the advice and actually
recommendation of several different
programs and from practitioners and um
um facilitators who had gone through
programs in both Oregon and Colorado
that we have spoken with where one of
the things that they really said is they
felt that after they graduated they were
kind of sort of left to drift. And so
the idea behind having the mentoring um
is after people graduate is really to
help again scaffold and give them some
additional support as they are opening
up and starting their practices and
really working with patients. I I do
agree with with Denali as far as it was
a very important thing to include the
case presentation aspect within the
requirements of it. But I do think that
in order to make sure that we have
providers who really feel supported to
have that mentorship, I think it's a
very important aspect to it and it's one
that quite a few people when we raised
it on up who had gone through programs
who may not have had a lot of experience
before really were grateful with that
idea and and thought that it was a good
idea. And so that's actually part of why
we have included that in there.
Um, and it actually can be a requirement
if it's post-certification
because what it does do is if a program
is not setting it up and we get
complaints on it, that particular
educational program could lose their
certification.
>> Thank you for that, Dominic. Um,
uh, I'm certified in EMD, not I'm
certified in EMDR and that's what they
have. they have a mentoring ship after
we have completed a program. Um even
though uh it it it's um we also do
groups and um uh individual supervision
uh and m mentoring. after that it um
really uh gives us a sense of um support
and also additional
uh education around that and also you
know it it boosts confidence in uh this
whole learning process. So I do agree
with with with this um I think it's
important to have
>> and and just as a note Brenda thank you
is for and you're right it's not a
requirement for the individual that they
participate in that 10 hours that's not
the intent of it. It's there to support
those who feel they need it to ensure
that they have that additional support.
But for example you yourself would if
you were going through the program would
not necessarily need those. they might
be beneficial and you might take
advantage of it, but it's not really
something that you would probably need.
So, we just wanted to ensure that it's
there and available for those who feel
they need it. But that at that point is
up to that graduate to decide whether
they want to provide it. And and I'll
give you a a real world example is um
with some of the programs that I where I
teach students at UN M, we actually have
some of that mentoring that's available.
And there are some students after they
graduate who do take advantage of it and
there are others that do not. And it may
be that they are getting that support
elsewhere through other means in which
case they're not just they're just not
doing it but it is available to them.
And we have Larry.
Larry you are in mute.
Thanks, Tom. Um, so I I'm I'm a little
concerned about here where we say case
presentation, consultation included in
practicum hours. Um, how do you how do
you see that actually happening? I'm
seeing that in the practicum hours,
they're actually involved with people.
There's people that are there. They're
watching them. But I I see that what
we're talking about in this other one is
where they're they're independent.
They're doing the session. They're
meeting with people like in the memory
model, listening to their cases. So, I
don't think they're the same thing. I I
think they're they're different
>> and and I would disagree on that, Larry.
I do think that they are very much the
same sort of situation. And if you look
at the hours with regard to it, um they
really it's 80 hours total that add up.
Um and this is of course after the low
acuity because the one thing we did
specify is it does need to be with you
know two of the last several patients
that they are working with. Um and so uh
the situation here would be we have 80
hours that are between that general
practicum and the preparatory in
integrative. So that's 80 hours in
total. Um whereas in the other proposal,
if you add all of that on up, again,
you're looking at a very similar amount
of hours because you have the 24 hours
with the low acuity. Um and and mind
you, I'm not including the low acuity on
the other side, but then you have the 12
hours of group work, 24 hours of the
supervised practice, and then 18 hours
of case presentation. And so if you look
at that, that ends up being 64 hours. um
whereas we have the 80 under that
portion of it. Um and so that's again if
you exclude that patients with low
acuity because we have that in both. So
that's why I say it is very similar.
It's just sort of structured a little
bit differently as far as part of it
including it.
>> Yeah. No, thanks Tom. I think the hours
are similar. It's more like the the
structure of having it be with a person
that you worked with independently and
presented it to a whole practice group.
I think they're a little bit different.
>> And Desbar,
>> hi. Thank you. I just wanted to kind of
just very briefly say, you know, to this
is all very um really good work just to
have the amount of care that everyone is
putting into discussing, supporting
um an individual through the
facilitation process.
um that it's just really wonderful to
see how we're really getting into the
minutia and having these conversations
about it because it really just like I
said it it it it is a huge example of
how much heart we have into the care
that we want to provide for everybody.
Um and to to just kind of sit with that
um as far as you know we can discuss
hours, we can discuss all these things.
I'm glad that you have the mentorship um
prospect in there. You know, it's the
same as just being married to possibly
someone for 58 years. God bless my
parents. Um however they're able to do
it. You always find a new way of
learning about something through the
process of having that conversation and
being open to ex to examining how we're
there for each other and the new ways
and avenues in which we're providing
support. Um I just I think that all of
these um ideas of you know how much
education is in there um whether a
person who has just experienced you know
psilocybin for the first time and wants
to like dive into helping and care
taking care of others. I know that again
like as I was trying to do the
facilitation pro uh program um and I did
not finish it but it it's amazing to
hear the the real life examples and
stories of people being facilitators and
coming up against you know their own
challenging experiences working with
someone to you know to get them to this
place um that's at their best and it's
not easy. So really taking the time
regardless of whether or not this turns
into best practices or rules is just so
valuable and important. And I know that
it's it's a lot for everybody, but I
just wanted to kind of tell everyone
thank you for putting such amount of
care and thought into really realizing
how much we have to put in support of
the rest of New Mexico.
>> Thank you, Desba. Thank you. Um, I
wanted to just go um briefly into the
chat here. Um, and I'm going to go from
the bottom up and that sound uh comment.
It sounds like it can be a requirement
if it is a postcertification.
Um,
Sky River, let's see. I'm sorry. I'm I'm
all over the place here. Um
Sky
Rivers had a question about clarity.
This is off topic by the way. She
mentions that uh HIPPO privacy in the
last EOL meeting uh was it discussed
about landlord approval and has there
been any movement on this challenge?
So that would uh be a question for
Dominic. Um,
I think we we I was uh in on that and uh
yeah, it it was a sticky subject. So, uh
I think we're going to be talking
further about that. Um let's see. Uh Kay
Hawk, I agree on the value of mentoring
while facilitators start practicing and
having it available ongoing.
Um and that's it. I mean for the
individual. Uh Kay Hawk also mentioned,
"I recently took advantage of mentoring
through Chris's EOL PC partly to see how
a mentoring program can work. It was
valuable even after 40 years of
practice." Thank you. Okay. Uh JD, uh
for interested students, what is the
estimated investment cost and time to
complete the training program? I don't
think we're there yet.
Um,
Denali uh said, "I misunderstood the
mentoring proposal and thought the
student was required to complete the 10
hours."
Uh, she understands now that training
program is required to offer, but
students can choose to participate if
needed. Having it optional makes sense
and I would draw my recommendation pull
mentoring requirement out. And then Sky
River said, "I only bring this up at
this as it was on the document as re the
requirement." I guess referring back to
her um the first question she had about
um client's privacy and uh from the
landlord's approval. So that I think is
another topic. Um anyone else have any
comments um or questions or suggestions
at this moment?
Larry, go ahead.
>> Dom, I may have misunderstood here what
I thought we were disagreeing about
in in what you're proposing full case
presentations like something like an
hour that meu is required as part of the
practicum.
>> I'm sorry, Larry. I missed a little bit.
You said full case presentations and I
missed that last bit.
>> So, so I was kind of, you know, um
advocating for the idea of having the
case presentations um uh being separate
and required but but somebody texted me
that their understanding is that that
the full case presentation something
like a memory model of you know which
might be 45 minutes or an hour
discussion is required in your
practicum.
I hadn't actually appreciated that.
Yeah, that's exactly what we're saying.
What we're saying is so say for example
uh you have in the last few um patients
that the student is working with as part
of the practicum they go through that
they they during that time should be and
of course throughout all of them taking
their notes getting ready as far as the
case and then they present and do that
full case presentation um with their
their mentors and with their um the
supervisors of the practicum as a part
of those practicum hours. So within that
80 hours of the general and the
preparatory sessions that case
presentation portion of it with those
real live patients occurs as a part of
those practicum hours. So when you talk
about like for example in the other
proposal where it was uh 18 hours that's
the they're going through the
preparatory phase they go through the
administration day they go through the
integrative sessions and then they
present and that's a 45 minute to an
hour hour and a half presentation
depending on the complexity of the case
would be exactly the same. It's just
included in the practicum hours in our
proposal. And that allows for
flexibility because you might have for
example a case that maybe you know
there's additional followup because
maybe the supervisor says you know what
you need to go back and that patient has
another uh session they're doing here
are some suggestions and have that
session and then do a little follow-up.
So it allows for additional flexibility
within that practicum to ensure that the
student is actually getting what they
need to get out of it and appropriate
case followup for the patient as well.
Okay. But there would not be like a a
practicum group that meets afterwards
and you listen to other people's
presentations. It would really just be
you working with your your practicum
teacher for the case presentation.
>> I it could actually be a combination. Um
which to be honest I I think a
combination is actually better than just
one over the other.
>> Agreed.
Now, Jeff,
>> go ahead, Senator.
>> Thank you all so much. Um, now I'm on a
different computer. Hey, I just wanted
to circle back to my previous comment
and ask uh
Dominic and and Larry what your thoughts
were about
the um how to incorporate post session
adverse impact training and how that
could be included in this.
Just welcome your thoughts on that.
>> Thank you, Senator. Um, and I actually
think both both proposals actually
included. It's a it really should be a
part of the continuity of care and
creating care plans because it shouldn't
be that we just finish after someone has
done their administration day or their
integrative sessions. It should be about
what is the plan for ongoing care. And
so I think actually both of the
proposals do include that. Um and it
really does that really does fall under
the continuity of care. We call in the
DO proposal it's about continuity of
care and creating care plans and then
some of the other aspects of it of
adverse uh reactions and things like
that falls in under various other topic
areas that need to be covered including
adverse events. Um and so I think that
is a part and I and I feel that it is a
part of both uh both um proposals.
Yeah. And thank you an within the
challenging experiences is how it's
worded in that in the other proposal.
>> Yeah. It might be good to speak to that
in the title itself or somehow it's just
so that you know that it's being
provided um or that it's required to be
provided or something.
That's and I know we're out of time.
That's the only vagory in your answer to
me, Dom. And I'm not saying it doesn't
exist. I just don't know it. Uh, does
continuity of care necessarily include
that? I mean, you're right. That's where
it would go, but do we know that it
would be? And how can we assure that it
would be?
>> Thank you.
>> Yeah.
Okay, we're coming up to the hour here.
Um, thank you Senator Steinborn for
that. Um, maybe, um, put that in the
language, the challenging experiences,
um, for the continuing, you know, care
for our patients that we're seeing. And
uh yeah uh that's just having more
safety and guardrails with what we're uh
trying to do here. And um I'm all for
safety definitely. Thank you.
So I guess that wraps things up um
today. Um, so I want to thank everyone.
Um, uh, Larry, uh, so Dominic, um, go
ahead,
>> Brenda. I just want to make sure
everybody does know is that, you know, I
I think we have that that there has been
a lot of progress and a lot of, you
know, uh, coming together on consensus
and a lot of it. Um, we are going to,
the department is going to be publishing
the rules, um, on Tuesday. And so um but
we will be taking all of this that's
been suggested you know under advisement
to look at it as far as that goes uh as
far as the different information being
presented. But again other than some
small areas quite frankly as far as
structure and everything else I feel
like it things are very close and I'm
really grateful to everybody and all of
the work that they've done. Um and and I
think that it's it's been really good.
Um, Denali, uh, the date it's going to
be, um, we're looking at the date being
in the beginning of October and I
believe the primary date we're looking
at is October 2nd, um, on that. Um, so,
uh, but we'll see that exactly uh,
again, we'll see that with the the final
notice because they are working with the
hearing officer on that aspect.
But yeah, anticipation, I should say, is
October 2nd. Um and as usual it will be
both um virtual and in person for the
hearing itself.
>> Okay. And I guess uh since we're getting
so close um I'm being very cautious to
try to vote on this yet. So um I think
um maybe just um holding off maybe a
little bit more. Dominic um uh on on
this. What do you think? I mean we're
going to take the different suggestions
and everything like I said under
advisement talk continue to talk you
know uh with um with our legal team um
so that you know to incorporate items in
um and and here's the other aspect as
well and I know this is a part people
tend to forget a bit is that once we do
publish the draft rules it doesn't mean
that we close off commentary and that we
close off public comment. In fact,
there's an entire process for that
public comment including up to uh the
rule hearing itself and to be able to
hear that and as we did in the last rule
for example, we do continue to make
changes and so um that that is part of
that process. So even if as we go
through this over the next day and a
half or so before the rules are
published then or I'm yeah are published
then you know if there's something
that's still not in there it doesn't
necessarily mean that it won't
necessarily change. It doesn't
necessarily mean that you know that
things are going to stay exactly the
same. They are not written in stone. Um
it is a part of the process so that we
hear even from a broad perspective and
broader from just these these committees
and the board meetings is that we hear
from more people about their thoughts,
their ideas and do we need to make
additional adjustments or changes. You
know it could be at any point in the
next two weeks somebody gets a brilliant
light bulb and bright idea and goes ah
why don't we just do this and we look at
it and we say that's not included. And
so we then go in and add it on in. So I
I think it's really it's up to you,
Brenda, as far as the this committee
itself goes, but we will be taking all
of these recommendations, looking at it
to see what potentially changes and
continuing to do so through the rule
hearing.
>> Thank you, Dominic. Um,
uh, does anyone have any other comments
at this at this time?
Okay, I just wanted to uh say in the
chat that Denali Wilson um quick note
for DOH on life-saving training
requirements throughout uh lifting the
small suggestion up again got a little
buried in the co copy text being
presented.
Um so at this point in time um I think
that we uh are very very close like
Dominic said um that um I would like to
hold off on a vote at [clears throat]
this point in time. I just want to be
very conservative. I really want us to
uh look at um anything else that might
be coming up because uh since we're so
close, I don't want to take a vote just
yet on what we're doing because um there
may be one or two hairs to split here
that may be of concerning for uh the
public and for the committee itself. So
um uh at this point in time uh maybe uh
I think the next uh education and
training meeting will be September 11th.
Um I haven't made a date for October uh
as of yet. Um that will be coming. Um so
uh I just wanted to thank everyone uh
especially Senator Steinborn for coming,
Larry Leman and Dr. Anne Metsz. uh
Denali um uh Greg Evans um and um
Dominic and everybody else. I have a I
missed that Desba um and Kate Hawk uh
for their contribution in the meeting
today. Um uh Sky has a comment to make.
Yeah, I just want clarity. On September
11th, 9 to 11 is the REI and 1 to 3 is
the board meeting. So, are you having a
meeting on the same day?
>> Um,
>> am I confused?
>> I think um I think we said um was it was
it the 11th? Um
>> 9 to 11 is racy, I thought.
>> Yeah, we just I I hadn't been able to
say anything just yet. So yeah, right
now on uh on the 11th we do have the REI
at 9 and the advisory board itself at
11. Um so we would have to choose a
different day.
>> I think that would
>> and the advisory board's at 1.
>> Oh, I'm sorry. Did I say nine again? My
apologies.
>> 11. [laughter]
>> Okay. 11 to three.
>> Okay. So the next training and education
meeting would be
did we say the 18th?
>> The 9 to 11 is the end of life meeting.
>> Yeah. And and uh department is not
available the afternoon of the 18th.
>> Oh, right. That's correct. That's
correct. Um
so um I thought we had um a meeting in
September.
>> Uh it was not yet scheduled.
>> Oh, it was not. Okay. Um so, uh can we
do that now? Can we schedule next
education and training?
>> Absolutely.
>> Okay. Um
>> we do have on the 4th uh either the 9 to
11 or the 1 to 3 is open. Uh the only
thing that I recommend with uh the 4th
and and this was when we were talking
about the board meeting as well is that
it is the Friday before 3-day weekend,
but the department is available. Um it
just sometimes other people are not. Um
if you did want to do it on the 4th, I
would recommend it being in the morning
at 9ine. Um but uh but again that would
be up to you, Brenda.
>> Um well, in that regard, um could we do
October 2nd?
>> Uh October.
>> Um we could. However, as I mentioned,
the rules hearing is going to be
scheduled, most likely scheduled that
morning.
>> Okay.
>> Um
>> well, uh let's go ahead and do Friday
the 4th. Um
uh preferably in the morning and whoever
shows shows. And um I think at that
point in time we'll we'll just go over
anything that um that people uh still
feel strongly about that we could
discuss and then uh just to make sure
that we're just having a meeting in
September
and it looks like um uh and then you'll
be gone Dominic on the 25th. Correct.
>> That is correct.
>> Okay.
All right. Um Okay. So then let's go
ahead and make it for um Friday morning
at 9 from 9 to 11 for education and
training
for September 4th.
>> Okay, we will get that on the calendar
and issued.
>> Okay, thank you very much.
>> Thank you. Thank you. It'll probably be
a short meeting since it's going to be
right the day before um you know uh a
three-day weekend. Um all righty. I
think uh we've made a lot of progress
here. I want to again thank everyone
again and um thank you for being here.
Hope to see you on the 4th. If not,
that's okay. Um we'll we'll just have a
loose discussion about um what um what
we've talked about today and the other
meetings in between.
>> And on behalf of the department, thank
you everyone. Hope you all have a great
weekend.